Finding aid for Stanley M. Swinton papers, 1935-1985
Bentley Historical Library
Stanley M. Swinton papers
1935-1985
Bentley Historical Library
Swinton, Stanley M. (Stanley Mitchell), 1919-1982
85517 Aa 2
5 linear feet
Journalist, foreign correspondent; correspondence, material accumulated as a journalist, articles, clippings, and other writings; and photographs.
The collection was the gift of Stanley M. Swinton (donor no. 5283 ) and came to the library in several accessions beginning in 1972.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Stanley Mitchell Swinton was born September 1, 1919 in Charlevoix, Michigan He began his journalism career by working as a reporter--before graduating to editor-in-chief-- for the Broadcaster, the newspaper for University High School in Ann Arbor. He wrote his first professional news story at the age of 15 and sold it for $1 to the Detroit Free Press. This first journalistic victory cemented his desire to become a journalist.
The son of University of Michigan Engineering Mechanics Professor Roy Swinton, Stanley Swinton attended the University of Michigan and earned his B.A. in 1940. While a student, he held two jobs: one as city editor of the Michigan Daily, the other working for the Detroit Free Press. Swinton also wrote short stories and won the prestigious Hopwood award. On graduation day, he attended the ceremonies in the morning and began working as an editor for the Associated Press that very afternoon. At the onset of World War II, he took military leave and worked as a front-line combat correspondent in North Africa, Italy, and southern France, writing for the Stars and Stripes, a newspaper published for American GI's overseas. After the war, he continued his work as an AP correspondent. In 1947-1948, he was named chief of bureau for Southeast Asia and in 1948-1950 for the Middle East. In the 1950s he married the former Helen Rhodes Meek of Scarsdale, NY and together they raised three sons. Swinton continued his rise through the ranks of the Associated Press and was named vice president, assistant general manager and director of World Services in 1972.
Swinton's career spans the years of intense conflict throughout the world and his papers provide insightful commentary on world events. He met and interviewed military rebels, presidents, religious leaders, prime ministers, sports and entertainment figures, and VIPs throughout the world. In 1950, he managed to get expelled from Egypt by King Farouk when he disclosed that Farouk planned to make the fiancée of a young Egyptian commoner his Queen against her will. Among his most famous stories is an eyewitness account of Fascist dictator Benito Mussolini hanging by his heels in a Milan square. In addition, he has interviewed Ho Chi-Minh, Ferdinand Marcos, the Shah of Iran, and Indira Gandhi. Swinton became a specialist on news media problems in third world countries and worked at many international conferences to improve relations between developing countries and the United States. His byline appeared in more than 100 countries.
Stanley Swinton remained with the Associated Press until he died of cancer August 29, 1982.
The Stanley Swinton papers include correspondence; dispatch files; notebooks relating to the death of Mussolini, the Malayan insurgency in the late 1940s, and the Indonesian revolutions; notes of interviews with Seni Premot of Thailand, Norodom Sihanouk of Cambodia, Ho Chi-Minh of Vietnam, Konrad Adenauer of West Germany, Joao Goulart of Brazil, Ferdinand Marcos of the Philippines, and Kim Jong Pil of South Korea. The bulk of Swinton's writings will be found in the collection, either in draft or in clippings of his articles. The series in the collection are Correspondence; Newspaper career; Writings, speeches, etc.; Personal and miscellaneous; Photographs; and Printed Material.
Brazil.; Egypt.; Germany.; Indochina.; Indonesia.; Italy.; Journalists -- United States.; Korea.; Korean War, 1950-1953.; Malaya.; The Michigan Daily.; American newspapers.; Philippines -- History -- 1946-1986.; Philippines -- History -- Japanese occupation, 1942-1945.; Prisoners of war -- Philippines.; Prisoners of war -- United States.; Thailand.; Vietnam.; World War, 1939-1945.; Campaigns and battles.; Egypt.; Guerrillas.; Indochinese War, 1946-1954.; Indonesia.; Italy.; Journalists -- United States.; Korea.; Korean War, 1950-1953.; Malaya.; National liberation movements.; Newspaper industry.; Soldiers.; Thailand.; Vietnam.; World War, 1939-1945.; CD-ROMs.; Photographs.; Adenauer, Konrad, 1876-1967.; Associated Press.; Goulart, João, 1918-1976.; Hồ, Chí Minh, 1890-1969.; Kim, Chong-p'il.; Marcos, Ferdinand E. (Ferdinand Edralin), 1917-1989.; Mussolini, Benito, 1883-1945.; Norodom Sihanouk, Prince, 1922-2012.; Seni Pramoj, M. R., 1905-; Sphinx (Fraternity: University of Michigan); Swinton, Roy Stanley, 1886-; Swinton, Stanley M. (Stanley Mitchell), 1919-1982.; Associated Press.; Blum, Léon, 1872-1950.; Mussolini, Benito, 1883-1945.; Niemöller, Martin, 1892-; Schuschnigg, Kurt, 1897-1977.; Sjahrir, Sutan, 1909-1966.
- Correspondence
  - Miscellaneous and undated (Box 1)
  - 1933-1939 (Box 1)
  - Undated--World War II (Box 1)
  - circa 1940-1941 (Box 1)
  - circa 1942 (Box 1)
  - 1940-1941 (Box 1)
  - 1942-1944 (Box 1)
  - 1945 (Box 1)
  - Undated 1945-1951 (Box 1)
  - January-June 1946 (Box 1)
  - July-December 1946 (Box 1)
  - 1947-1948 (Box 1)
  - 1949-1950 (Box 1)
  - January-June 1951 (Box 1)
  - July-December 1951 (Box 1)
  - 1952 (Box 1)
  - 1953 (Box 1)
  - 1954 (Box 1)
  - January-February 1955 (Box 1)
  - March-December 1955 (Box 1)
  - January-November 1956 (Box 1)
  - December 1956 (Box 1)
  - 1957 (Box 1)
  - 1958 (Box 1)
  - 1959 (Box 1)
  - 1960 (Box 1)
  - 1961-1965 (Box 1)
  - 1966 (Box 1)
  - 1967-1969 (Box 1)
  - 1970-1977 (Box 1)
  - 1978 (Box 1)
  - 1979-1980 (Box 1)
  - 1981 (Box 1)
  - 1982-1985 (Box 1)
  - Clare Booth Luce letters, clippings and miscellaneous (Box 1)
- Newspaper Career
  - Interviews and notes on interviews
    - Premier Seni Premot, Thai, 1946 (Box 2)
    - Norodom Sihanouk, Cambodia, 1946 (Box 2)
    - Ho Chi-Minh, Vietnam, 1946 (Box 2)
    - S. Swinton interviewed on Indochina, 1946 (Box 2)
    - Konrad Adenauer, West Germany, 1960 (Box 2)
    - Carlos P. Garcia, Philippines, 1960; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - João Goulart, Brazil, 1961 (Box 2)
    - Ferdinand Marcos, Philippines, 1970; 1973 (Box 2)
    - Kim Jong Pil, South Korea, 1973 (Box 2)
    - Mohammad Reza Shah Pahlevi, Iran, 1976 (Box 2)
  - Notebooks and notes
    - Death of Mussolini, 1945 (Box 2)
    - Malayan campaign, circa 1947 (Box 2)
    - Dutch-Indonesian Agreement, 1948 (Box 2)
    - Indonesian Revolution, 1966 (Box 2)
    - General, undated; circa 1965; 2 volumes (Box 2)
    - Interview notes and transcripts, circa 1946-1976 (Box 2)
  - Dispatches
    - Michigan Daily, 1938 (Box 2)
    - Stars and Stripes, 1943-1945 (Box 2)
    - Southeast Asia, 1945-1948; 6 folders (Box 2)
    - Egypt, 1948-1950 (Box 2)
    - Korea, 1950-1951; 7 folders (Box 2)
    - Indonesia, 1966 (Box 2)
    - General, 1951-1960; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - General, 1961-1976; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Other materials
    - Miscellaneous memoranda (Box 2)
    - Expense accounts (Box 2)
  - Newsclipping file
    (includes both articles by Swinton and about him)
    - Michigan Daily, 1936-1940 (Box 2)
    - World War II, 1941-1945 (Box 2)
    - Southeast Asia, 1945-1948; 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Southeast Asia, 1966; 1978 (Box 2)
    - Egypt, 1948-1950; 1978 (Box 2)
    - Korean War, 1950-1951; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Latin America, general, 1960-1963; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - General
      - 1938-1939 (Box 2)
      - 1951-1960, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - 1961-1970 (Box 3)
      - 1971-1977 (Box 3)
    - Personal (about or with mention of Swinton)
      - 1940-1950 (Box 3)
      - 1951-1960, 2 folders (Box 3)
      - 1961-1962 (Box 3)
      - 1963-1965 (Box 3)
      - 1966 (Box 3)
      - 1967-1968 (Box 3)
      - 1969-1978 (Box 3)
      - General, circa 1940-1984 (Box 3)
      - Asia, 1947-1975 (Box 3)
      - Latin America, 1960-1979 (Box 3)
      - World News, 1945-circa 1980 (Box 3)
- Writings, speeches, etc.
  - Newspaper and other Articles
    - Miscellaneous, circa 1938-1965 (Box 3)
    - Asia, circa 1946-1978 (Box 3)
    - Australia, 1973 (Box 3)
    - Europe, 1951-1973 (Box 3)
    - Dutch-Indonesian Conflict, 1946-1947 (Box 3)
    - Greece, 1981 (Box 3)
    - Latin America, circa 1960-1979 (Box 3)
    - Michigan, circa 1939-1966 (Box 3)
    - Technology and the Press, circa 1959-1981 (Box 3)
    - World News, miscellaneous, circa 1950-1970 (Box 3)
    - World War II, 1942-1966 (Box 3)
  - Article Titles, 1945-1969 (Box 3)
  - Book Reviews, 1938-1982 (Box 3)
  - Speeches and Remarks, 1969-1979 (Box 3)
  - Speeches and lectures, 1945-1971; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Autobiography, 1935-1936 (Box 3)
  - Student newspaper, University High School, 1935-1936 (Box 3)
  - Television script, "Mussolini,", 1957-1958; 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Book reviews, 1958-1960 (Box 3)
  - Short story file, most written, 1935-1939; 15 folders (Box 3)
- Personal and Miscellaneous
  - General, circa 1930-1970 (Box 4)
  - Agents' Training Course (Corps of Military Police), 1942 (Box 4)
  - Appointment Book, 1972 (Box 4)
  - Associated Press, 1937-1956 (Box 4)
  - Associated Press, 1957-1971 (Box 4)
  - Associated Press, 1974-1979 (Box 4)
  - Associated Press, 1981-1982 (Box 4)
  - Cabot Award, 1981 (Box 4)
  - Fiction, circa 1935-1938 (Box 4)
  - Invitations, circa 1947-1978 (Box 4)
  - School
    - University High, 1935-1936 (Box 4)
    - University of Michigan, 1936-1937 (Box 4)
      (include fragmentary diary)
  - World War II and later, circa 1940-1949 (Box 4)
  - Personal file, orders, passes, etc.
    - Miscellaneous and undated (Box 4)
    - 1938-1940 (Box 4)
    - 1941-1950, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - 1951-1960, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - 1961-1966 (Box 4)
    - 1967-1974 (Box 4)
    - Invitations, 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Distinguished Alumni Award, 1966-1967 (Box 4)
  - Roy S. Swinton, prison camp reminiscence, 1945 (Box 4)
  - Obituaries of friends of S. Swinton, scattered dates (Box 4)
  - Interview of Swinton and others on "Third World & the Press,", 1978 (Box 4)
- Photographs
  The Photographs series (0.5 linear feet) covers the years 1936-1980 and contains hundreds of photos, a small number of negatives, and a few slides. The photos illustrate in great detail his work during World War II. They also document his many interviews with noteworthy persons. Also included is the famous photograph of the hanging body of Mussolini (Swinton can be seen standing in the background). The majority of the photos are in black and white, including those in the 1960s and 1970s.
  - Portraits
    - 1936-1969 (Box 5)
    - 1970-circa 1978 (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous Activities, 1937-1980; 3 folders (Box 5)
  - Associated Press--General, 1949-1980 (Box 5)
  - Associated Press bureaus and other newsrooms, 1951-circa 1960 (Box 5)
  - Associated Press dinner, 1968 (Box 5)
  - Associated Press Treaty Signings, 1958-1980 (Box 5)
  - Egypt, 1948-1950 (Box 5)
  - Entertainment Figures, circa 1951-1969 (Box 5)
  - Foreign Officials, 1948-1977 (Box 5)
  - Indochina, 1945-1948 (Box 5)
  - Indonesia
    - 1945 (Box 5)
    - 1946-1948 (Box 5)
      (includes photos of Swinton with Soetan Sjahrir)
  - Italy, 1944-1945 (Box 5)
    (includes photos of Léon Blum, Martin Niemöller, and Kurt von Schuschnigg after release from prison camp, and of the site of Mussolini's death)
  - Korea, 1950-1951 (Box 5)
  - Malaysia and Singapore, 1945-1948 (Box 5)
  - Pope Pius XII, 1954 (Box 5)
  - Presidents of the World
    - 1945-1978 (Box 5)
    - Ferdinand Marcos, 1966 (Box 5)
  - Sports Figures, 1960-1961 (Box 5)
  - Thai, 1945-1948 (Box 5)
  - United States officials and other public figures, 1951-1980 (Box 5)
  - Negatives, circa 1941-1980 (Box 5)
  - Slides of Indira Gandhi, 1966 (Box 5)
  - CD-ROM photos of Stanley Swinton chosen for his study wall (Box 5)
- Printed Material
  - Voice of Free Indonesia, 1946-1947; 17 issues (Box 5)
  - Pantja Raja, 1947 (Box 5)
  - Vietnam-American Friendship Association Review, 1945-1946; 5 issues (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous university publications containing articles by Swinton, 1937-1939 (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous, scattered dates (Box 5)